John thank you for coming a bit early my
pleasure because my other guest
apparently didn't show up so you are oh
that sounds familiar how you doing this
today man you're doing all right I'm
okay thanks how are you I am doing great
John you're easily one of my favorite
people to talk to oh thank um you have
led such a colorful interesting at times
U painful life um but nevertheless it
has led
to like I said colorful life
um the Reon I what you in I I've been
focused on what has been taking place in
Syria where turkey the US even Israel
have put money resources in having
jihadists
reignite come out of ilip screaming with
a full-blown military of terrorists um
oh I'm sorry Freedom loving terrorist
Freedom Fighters yeah Freedom loving
right freedom fighting terrorists um who
are chopping off heads as they go along
and we back this stuff we pay for this
stuff we I mean these guys are driving
an American um um armaments weapons like
tanks and
whatnot why go back for us into the way
that the CIA has ingratiated itself into
these al- Qaeda groups in order to get
these groups to fight for America and
how is this even done like meaning how
does the CIA a getting contact with a
terrorist like who who are they even
talking to in order to get their hands
on is this just going through turkey and
turkey talks to the terrorists how does
this work in practice uh yeah in part
there there are several different ways
to do it and and this is a very we
should preface this jamor by saying this
is a very complicated situation but the
easy part is that the United States is
wrong so let's talk about that the way
you get in touch with uh a terrorist
group is multifold number one you go
through the Turks number two you might
have a recruited asset that you then
send to the leadership number three
maybe you've captured some of these guys
and you sit down and you say look here's
our position and then you lay it out
that you want to actually cooperate work
Finance
arm their their organization so there's
several different ways to do it now I I
said it comp uh uh it was
complicated for a number of reasons
number one the United States does not
have any genuine national interests in
this fight right I mean let's let's just
call it spade a spade here Syria doesn't
have any any appreciable amount of oil
number one uh well just I am G to quible
with that just a little
bit from from us perspective I think we
are looking at this as a global conflict
and these are just fronts like if we
were in the second world war but we
shouldn't though but we shouldn't look
at this as a global conflict is my point
number
one you know what let me tell you a very
quick little story in 2000 my two oldest
Sons wanted me to take them to Madison
Square Garden to see a WWE professional
wrestling match so I took him I hated it
I didn't understand any of it
and I said to them finally about 15
minutes in I don't I don't get it which
one's the good guy and my oldest son
said that's just it Dad there is no good
guy and that's the situation in Syria
there is no good guy now with that
said whether you like his politics or
not whether you believe that he has
killed his own people or not with gas or
chemicals or whatever and there are
serious doubts that he ever did Bashar
alasa
is the only thing standing in the
way of the complete and total
annihilation of Syria's quite large
Christian Community all right there are
Christians in the parliament there are
Christians in the cabinet in senior
positions including the foreign minister
and if Bashar Al Assad is overthrown by
these Jihadi
radicals every Christian in Syria is
either going to be executed or forced
out of the country
so the decision that the United States
has made is this is a black and white
issue we don't like Assad usad is with
the Russians we're with the Kurds the
Turks are against the Kurds the Kurds
don't have the manpower to take over the
whole country but Isis
does so we're going to Ally ourselves
with Isis
light which is the the Islamic Rebels
formerly known as the anus front
which before that was known as
Al-Qaeda now can you imagine we've
Allied ourselves with Al-Qaeda now they
have promised us that they would
moderate their politics they haven't but
they have gladly accepted American
weapons American still chopping off
heads they're still chopping off heads
exactly but this is what we've done
because we don't like Assad and we don't
like the fact that the Russians are in
Syria propping up Assad that's really
what it comes down
to and it's just astonishing to me I
like I at some point you realize you're
not the good guys and this is one of
those moments where you we are just not
good guys I mean it's amazing to me that
we're willing to do this just to take
down a side and do you think this is
being provoked because of what's
happening in Ukraine like they are
effectively losing so poorly in Ukraine
that they've expanded the battlefield
out to Syria
yes I do I do very very much so I was
having a conversation with a friend
about this just yesterday and he said
you know one of the interesting things
is that there is literally no leadership
in the west right now the the American
president is weak uh the Canadian prime
minister is weak the the British prime
minister is falling on his face the
French government collapsed yesterday
the German government is in the process
of collapsing there's just no leadership
in the west and so what happens in a
situation like that is that the US
government flails around looking for a
quick and easy war in which it can make
an impact and come out looking more
strongly Syria is not the not the way to
do that but in Washington nobody seems
to either understand or to care but why
do they think that though I mean like
for example and let me get your take on
this
when you would think at the very least
in the old days
that there was some
strategic overarching plan when they're
looking at the world and looking at the
globe that doesn't seem to be the case
here it seems like they slept walked
into Syria thinking well we're at the
West we have economic and Military
domain so we can tell the Russians that
we can totally win this fight in Ukraine
there didn't seem to be any planning on
it they seem to just fell as backwards
into it well it's let me interrupt you
it it's akin to the Russian position
during the Vietnam war
where the Russians didn't want to get
directly directly involved so they just
armed the North Vietnamese did it over
the course of years and finally the
Americans were driven out the American
calculus is the same in Ukraine we're
not going to get directly involved We're
not gonna have American troops fighting
Russian troops but we'll arm the
ukrainians to the to their eyeballs and
just hope that they can bleed the
Russians even if it takes 20 years and
then Force the Russians out and that's
actually not the way it's working out
yeah that fail miserably that didn't
happen that way at all and it seems like
they've State this idea this the reason
I I quible with this idea that it wasn't
in our interest in Syria is because it
seems that they they're looking at this
is existential from the standpoint of
Western control like if they lose in
Ukraine then the very purpose of NATO
the very purpose of this notion of
Western control World also fall dies
with it I mean correct came from wrong
on that because that's they have
escalated over and over and over again
and they don't seem to be able to accept
the fact Ukraine is a loss they just
don't seem to be able to do it well
because if Ukraine is a loss then what
happens to the post-war planning I mean
the notion that you declare uh Ukraine a
non a major non-n Ally goes out the
window Ukraine can't join NATO uh as a
as an official member Ukraine probably
then can't join the European Union
although there's a precedent for that in
Cyprus but if if the ukrainians lose
this conflict it really screws things up
for the
Americans and then what do we do there's
no plan there's no post-war plan for
what happens if Ukraine
loses wow the CIA when it's dealing with
I would imagine so one of the things
that see more pointed out was that
during the Bush Administration that
there was a turn with this idea that
okay in order for us to get Iran we need
to get Syria and so back during the
George Bush Administration they started
working with terrorist organizations to
try to make connections with those
organizations with the idea of creating
a resistance against Assad or for that
matter even his dad at one point um to
try to either overthrow to undercut him
with the idea of moving into Iran now
this goes back to Wesley Clark saying
that the US government was trying to
take down seven governments in five
years which is again astonishing when
you really think about it I mean the
number of lives that they were willing
to basically kill in order to pull this
policy over with I remember a
conversation with you where you told me
how you were sitting at a meeting and
Dick Cheney pointed out they were going
to try to go through all of those
countries into
Iran um that seems to be what they're
doing and it seems to be what they're
still doing now correct me if I'm wrong
but now I think that well you know the
the Pentagon the CIA the state
department they have these o on the
shelf or off the-shelf policies right so
we've got a a a policy that's just
sitting there on the Shelf to invade
Iran and to uh overthrow the government
but it's it's not just Iran specific we
have we have off-the-shelf plans for two
dozen countries like that just in the
event that all hell breaks loose you
know or or we see an inn or there's an
uprising in Iran we can move in and take
advantage of it um what you're talking
about is a a meeting that I was in the
night before we invaded uh Iraq and uh
it was General Tommy Franks who was the
commander of Central Command in Tampa
giving his um his final pre-attack
briefing in which he said that we're
going to cross the border in the morning
and if all goes as planned he said we
can be in teron by August this was uh
the end of
February 2003 of course that didn't
happen because there's a fundamental
misunderstanding of the Middle East and
as we've come to learn of other
countries around the world where we're
not greeted as liberators we're greeted
as Invaders and occupiers and so we're
resisted they're not going to throw
flowers at us which is what one of the
senior directors at the National
Security Council said in that meeting
when we cross the border they're going
to throw flowers at us no they're not
they're going to throw hand grenades at
us to try to stop us from invading and
occupying their
country so it's the same situation now
yeah I made a point on a show the other
day and I'm gonna stick by
it um the Iranians hate Donald Trump
Donald Trump hates the Iranians Donald
Trump murdered kasum yeah the the head
of the alud force and there's a there's
a very special kind of hatred of Donald
Trump in
Iran with that said there are credible
reports that Elon Musk with met with the
Iranian ambassador to the United Nations
two weeks do you believe that because
Iran said it didn't happen I do 100 per.
I do you can't you can't hide a meeting
like that so they deny it for public
consumption not absolutely okay and the
reason I think that it happened is
because you remember the old phrase only
Nixon could go to China right right
Richard Nixon had spent his entire adult
life attacking Chinese communism and
then it was Nixon that went to China and
made peace with the Chinese and
established diplomatic relations with
the Chinese only Trump could go to
Iran and I think something may be a foot
at least in the very preliminary
stages where you know maybe we've
underestimated Trump or maybe his
domestic craziness has influenced us to
the point where we just dismiss
everything that he does maybe there's
something to this even with this Pro
radically
pro-israel um contingent of lunatics
that he bring into his administration
even with them yeah you think that he
may but what makes them any less
radically pro-israel lunatic uh than
what the Biden Administration has given
us um heges heges believe one of those
people believing that um Christ is going
to return in the middle of a war in the
Middle East yeah and if you could
provoke that war and build a temple on
the mound that Jesus returns correct
that's I mean you know what that looks
like in regards to policy I agree with
you may not necessarily be that
different in the way it's
expressed um that is pretty damn
outrageous and it's like if these are
the people that he's bringing into this
Administration that gives me concerns in
but it was the same kind of people that
were in the the Reagan Administration
and the George W Bush Administration we
cycle through these Evangelical lunatics
every time there's a republican
Administration nothing comes of it you
know and this is a very
longstanding uh Evangelical position
that you've got to support the Israelis
because you've got to support a policy
that that demands that all Jews return
to Israel because only then can Jesus
come back and right it's the apocalypse
and blah blah blah and then the Rapture
and then everybody that's good go happen
it's all nuts yeah and not biblically
based by the way they they believe it
though there's the word rapture never
appears in the Bible anywhere it's made
up it's an it's a a late 19th century
invention of a of American Baptists even
European Baptists don't believe in the
Rapture interesting interesting
I'm curious from your te how is the CIA
involved in all of this stuff like
meaning yeah that's a good question this
is one of those situations tomorrow
where the CIA does as it's told uh
remember the CIA
is the CIA is not a policy uh agency
it's a policy support agency and so if
the if the policy coming out of the
White House is that the CIA should you
know make nice with Al-Qaeda or with
Isis then they make nice with Al-Qaeda
or Isis if the if the position of the
white house is that it works along with
the government of turkey to encourage uh
Islamic radicals to take idlib and H
that's what it does then that's what it
does yeah it does how are they paid like
meaning when the CIA goes to some of
these groups big
beards um Warriors of Allah that are
free free democracy loving terrorists
yes at some point they're getting paid
they're driving around in military Beast
they're they're carrying you know these
special they're getting training from
Ukraine's ukrainians in regards to drone
Warfare I mean like they were this is a
full like hundreds of thousands of thick
bearded men going into war how on Earth
does the CIA get money appropriate from
Congress to give and no no oh no no let
me let me I'll correct that first and
then answer your question more
specifically uh the black budget is
never delineated the Appropriations are
never delineated it's just a number and
then once the number is approved by
Congress the CIA spends it in any way
they want so there's no line item that
says no there's no oversight at all to
this the gang of four the the chairman
and vice chairman of the two oversight
committees will have access to the
information but even the other members
of the committee won't have access to
the information that's number just the
number so the CIA says I need a trillion
dollars and they say okay here's it
all right and then they'll whisper into
the ears of the chairman and the vice
chairman of the House and Senate
committees what the numers for and then
they just go like this so number one
number two I'm I'm fond of saying I've
been saying for 20 years 30 years
intelligence is a cash business I'm not
joking with you jamor when I say we were
throwing money out of the side of
helicopters in
Afghanistan I drove from Islamabad to
lore in 2002 with $2 million in cash in
duffel bags are you serious I did
indeed yeah it's a cash business you
deal in cash now it's changing where you
can deal in Bitcoin there's no nobody's
tracing Bitcoin it's not possible to
change to trace Bitcoin you just hand
somebody a thumb drive a digital wallet
and you say knock yourselves out
it's that
easy oh John that is I mean I guess
that's is how it would have to be at
once some level right otherwise you can
trace it exactly but it is a little
disturbing they are somebody is taking
duffel bags of money I say all right
here you are now you're well paid go buy
this gun go buy this well listen when
when we thought we had identified the
location of abuaba we knew that this was
going to be a big and expensive
operation and so I put out a cable
region wide and I said I need $10
million in cash and so one station sent
a million a small station sent $200,000
another station sent 2 million it was
all in cash and it's flying in in
diplomatic pouches and I put it all in a
duffel bag and then I drove with a
colleague to Karachi not to Karachi to
lore and we we started buying real
estate we bought two houses to use as
safe houses and interrogation centers
we're throwing money at you know
Al-Qaeda people to rat out their
colleagues we're buying guns and
battering rams and ammunition and
satellite dishes and night vision
goggles and you know that that's just
the nature of the job and so when we
were working with turkey for example at
that point turkey takes the suspense and
they well turkey will take this suspense
we we will reimburse them every cent
okay yeah wow I'm sorry I just got
I just WRA my head around that like
there's so much money that it's just
slashing around in cash that is paying
people um for disreputable actions all
right so they call out there's a number
that comes up even though they don't
exactly know what the number is for
Congress has to pay money for that that
money is effectively given in cash and
that cash is sprad around to whoever is
going to be involved in the operation um
all right
so then at that point though how does
the CIA get them to do X or Y and I
guess this point this is a conversation
with turkey Turk is I intered on this on
with erdogan having his own objectives
the the yes the objectives have to
coincide the the national interests have
to coincide the Turks have to want
exactly the same thing that the
Americans want because if they don't
it's not going to work and you're gonna
have to go It Alone case this case yes
the the the national interests are
identical not to say that it's the right
thing to do but the national interests
are identical we hate Assad the Turks
hate Assad here's a chance for us to
overthrow
Assad
again if you're an Israeli I think the
Israelis are making a serious mistake
here well they just want chaos they just
want want chaos yeah fighting each other
which over the course of a couple of
weeks might be a good thing if you're
Israeli because it'll distract the bad
guys while they fight each other but the
devil you know is better than the devil
you don't and Assad has never been a
threat to Israel
never but what happens if Isis is in
charge in gonna say if the government
Falls meaning if all of these people if
the us if the Turks if the Israelis get
what they want and aside Falls and you
get this calip over all of Syria where
all of the Christians are killed all of
the other groups Muslim groups that they
don't like are killed and beheaded then
what exactly you know I've I've been to
Damascus I don't know if you have been
but I was able to go to a working
synagogue in Damascus right there's a
community of Syrian Jews they are
perfectly free to practice their faith
as they as they see fit they're loyal to
the Assad government because because it
respects freedom of religion believe it
or not safe yeah and keeps them safe um
there are churches all over Syria I went
to Sunday liturgy at at a Greek Orthodox
Cathedral in Damascus there Catholic
churches in Damascus well if Assad's
overthrown everybody's dead and and
they're going to bulldoze these Isis and
Al-Qaeda people are going to bulldo the
churches they're going to bulldo the
synagogues everybody's either going to
be killed or driven out of the country
and then what are the Israelis going to
do when they've got an Al-Qaeda or Isis
Le government right on their border I
know but Al-Qaeda never attacked Israel
because it's never had the ability to
remember it killed Jews in
India in the uh in the Mumbai attacks
back in what was it 2008 I guess um but
they never had proximity to Israel to
attack Israel if they're right on the
border you know the sky's the limit is
the thinking that okay well we can't
militarily attack aide we can't create a
justification for the US or anybody else
to attack Assad in that way however
jihadists hedg Hoppers oh they're fair
game sure attack them and the new
government that we put into place will
be a py and an ally of us Israel and be
antagonistic to Russia is that the
thought that that is the thought okay
and and the NRA front now called the ja
HTS or something yeah
yeah I forget now whatever they whatever
they're calling themselves today keep
changing things um they they have made
they have a policy of promoting the
notion that they are moderates they're
not moderates right they're head
choppers as you say chers but they have
successfully convinced the United States
or maybe the United States wants to
believe that they're moderates so that
as we arm them and finance them we can
sleep at
night they know that's not true I mean
like I I don't I don't believe for a
moment that the U I believe look I think
we were dealing I think these people are
sociopath many many in the US they have
to know yes they they have to know they
know but but at the same time they think
that they are so smart and so good that
when Assad's overthrown they can
successfully convince these these
radicals uh to truly moderate and work
with us in the International Community
and remember there's a bigger fight here
this is the Americans versus the
Russians just happens to be in
Syria yeah it's just another front in
this kind of conflict is there an open
line between the Russians and the US in
Syria no not in Syria specifically there
is an open line from from the Pentagon
to the Russian uh Ministry of Defense
but Ambassador Antonov uh the recently
departed ambassador to the United States
said that it's essentially defunct
there's no communication that's so
dangerous I I so I went to the Putin
Biden Summit um I was covering that for
the network and I remember being I guess
at this point um naive and somewhat
optimistic because it seems at at the
time that Joe Biden and Putin were
saying the same thing like they were
like literally and the Press was
attacking Joe Biden because of it like
what do you mean you didn't read them WR
you know this type of stuff and Biden
starts screaming at a reporter at one
point saying you don't understand trying
to get across to the reporter look we're
dealing with nuclear Powers here we need
to have some level of communication in
order to know what each other is doing
so we don't necessarily make any
mistakes in our like that we don't
mispredict what the other one is doing
okay well that's out the window now
correct yeah it's out the window there's
no negotiation there's no communication
there's no hope for any kind of forward
progress in bilateral relations it's
just not
happening what about through the back
door what about William B give me your
take on um Burns Burns seemed to be a
bit better Diplomat than Anthony blinkin
oh yeah there's no comparison I I know
both Bill Burns and Tony blinkin um I've
known Tony blinkin for years actually
not well we're not buddies or anything
but I've known him for a very long time
he seems like a lunatic no no no he's a
lovely guy he's just in completely over
his head oh yeah he's a lovy just came
out and said you need to send your kids
to a losing War yeah
yeah well because that's his job he's
the Secretary of State he has to promote
the policy but Tony listen Tony's a very
bright Harvard educated bureaucrat
but Tony's first job out of Harvard was
as a junior legislative Aid to Joe Biden
he worked his way up through the Biden
Senate Office yeah then he became the
legislative director for Joe Biden then
when Biden became the uh chairman of the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee Tony
became the staff director when Biden was
elected vice president Tony became his
National Security adviser then Biden had
Tony uh installed as the deputy
secretary of state and then when Biden
was elected president Tony became the
secretary of state so he literally every
job he's had in his adult life since he
graduated from college was with Joe
Biden wow yeah he's never really lived
in the real
world Bill Burns on the other hand bill
Burns is the consumate Diplomat yeah
Burns is one of these guys that was
respected across party lines at the
state department the CIA the defense
department the White House I wrote an
oped when Burns was firsted CIA director
saying finally an adult in the room I
saw that I read that I think but it says
a lot when you've got these
extraordinarily sensitive negotiations
between Hamas and the Israelis where you
don't send your secretary of state
exactly you send your CIA director to
conduct diplomacy that says a lot about
Tony blink as much about Tony blinkin as
it says about Bill Burns tell me
something else tell the audience
something about the CIA that they don't
know that they' be surprised
about I think there's a lot that people
would be surprised about the CIA you
know it's it's a group of tens of
thousands of very very bright um very
patriotic people who are infected by the
disease called group think and they end
up
analyzing policy in this little tiny box
so even though these are some of the
smartest people that our country can can
offer they don't offer the smarttest
analysis they don't influence policy the
way that they probably might be able to
and uh you know that old that old German
adage that I I was just following orders
is really the Mantra at the CIA really
yeah and
so may may I add one thing Jamar I'm
sorry to interrupt you no no this is why
I have always always opposed Military
Officers as heads of the
CIA because you become a four-star
general
by saying yes sir right that's how you
make it through your career yes sir
right you need a CIA director who has
the balls to stand up and say Mr
President let me tell you why that is a
terrible
idea and we don't have CIA directors
like that policy Trump's intelligence
under normal circumstances yeah wow John
man thank you for this I I I'm always
fascinated by these conversations just
like my pleasure like the idea that
people sitting in room and come up with
yeah we're going to get all these people
killed because of policy yeah and it
doesn't seem to register like hey you're
getting people killed like we don't we
don't learn our lessons from history you
know John krey famously said in 1972 do
you want to be or to paraphrase John KY
do you want to be the person who sends
his his son to die uh you know for for a
lost cause at the end of the Vietnam War
and here we are decades later we've not
learned that lesson doing the same thing
to die for a
mistake wow yeah it's just astonishing
John man thank you for this John Kaku
pleasure he is a former CIA officer John
what do you where are you now where do
people find you now substack everything
I do I put on substack and I am very
soon in January going to begin a
50 event 90day speaking tour of the the
United Kingdom are you yeah starting
with four dates in Ireland January 31st
in Belfast February 1st in Dublin
February 3rd in Waterford and February
4th in Cork and then I go to uh five
five nights in London now what is the
conversation going to be on it's a
conversation with CIA officer John
kiraku so we can talk about anything
people want to talk about oh that is
fantastic John it's all all on substack
thank you thank you man I appreciate
all right we have come